um that's the part that's missing in
other words you have the information you
you know
that um you've read about the four noble
truths you you have some recognition of
the three
characteristics whichever aspect of the
teaching you you might want to to focus
on but um you're not living in according
to it in accordance with it you still
live and it says um the inside of
everything that is liable to arise is
liable to
cease so um some people might have heard
of this uh Parable um I think it's from
the Hindu tradition that says
that um what you think is a
snake is actually a
rope Therefore your suffering on account
of that snake
is illusory it's it's uh it's a mistake
because it's um you're deluded you know
the Ultimate
Reality and um if you investigate
closely you would realize that that view
was implied in
um most of the modern understandings of
what wisdom
is um people expect to gain some sort
of access to some ultimate hidden
reality as a result of their meditation
practice and then there might be
different ideas as to what exactly that
Ultimate Reality
is um of course it would be equated in
Nana if you're a Buddhist you'll be
equated with uh whatever God if you're a
Christian um various side things the
point is you conceive the solution to
this problem of suffering your life to
be this higher reality that you still
haven't accessed so
is that is there a problem with that and
uh why what's the difference between
that and uh what the Buddha was teaching
in the
sutas well if you're looking for some
higher or Ultimate Reality you you have
already turned your back to what is
presently in front of
you mhm and as a result of that you will
not be able to understand what is
actually already taking place just now
mhm so how are you going to understand
the origin of your present suffering if
you keep turning your back towards it
but what
if what if somebody might say but the
things that are present here are
irrelevant because they're not real so
should I concern myself with them mhm
yeah that's about a pernicious view
right the
what or it might also be maybe not that
it might be said that maybe not just
that they're not relevant but like you
have a distorted perception of them like
you have dust in your eyes or something
so therefore you can't trust your your
perception but you see to say that
things are to say that things are not
real um you're still talking about
things so the things have to be there
first and then you regard them as not
real mhm as opposed to real but is
always of things that you say that they
are not real so that position actually
in and of itself or doesn't add up
something might be illusory but it
doesn't mean that it isn't there m as an
illusion it is still real and as such
you suffer on account of that and that
suffering is not because those things
are ucer well in other words where the
ucer well in other words where the
things are ucer or not is secondary to
the fact that you're suffering that's
the point yeah and
um the thing is it might factually give
you a sense of release of yourself from
your suffering but it's it's for the
wrong reason because like like you just
said the things were never the problem
to begin with so it's kind of the like
it it goes very deeply and it's not just
a a
um not just a course view of again
Ultimate Reality it's um it's the view of
Reality it's um it's the view of
management in the most General sense
that you might often when people have um
whatever interpersonal problems or
anger against someone or um something
like that they would think the solution
is
to kind of reinterpret your relationship
with that person so tell yourself as I
think that's called in Psychology
cognitive reframing which obviously you you don't
reframing which obviously you you don't
need the Buddha for uh just telling
yourself that you know this person is
whatever they're doing this to you
because um their childhood was was kind
of problematic or maybe they they're
having a bad day and through through
kind of um reframing the situation in that
of um reframing the situation in that
sense you quote unquote Escape The
Suffering alternatively you might Escape The
alternatively you might Escape The
Suffering by telling yourself oh well
all these are just all of these
situations are just um constantly
changing processes there's nothing
there's no inherent Essence in this and
through kind of repeating that view to
yourself you eventually kind of stop
feeling that which was bothering you but
the thing is as the said
um what is the origin of
suffering is it the fact that you didn't
have the access to this to these
perceptions to these higher perceptions
is that what he said
mhm so it's he said it's craving that's
the origin of suffering so when is
craving
there when is craving there
yeah well craving will always be in
relation to something MH and so whether
that thing is not real or illusory or
that it doesn't matter but more
specifically in relation to what is
their craving well I would say feeding
mhm yeah exactly so in other words the
problem is that when things are
unpleasant in other words when you
haven't still managed to reframe the
thing so that you don't feel the pain
anymore you're liable to
craving so if you have to then re-explain and
so if you have to then re-explain and
reframe the thing so that it's not felt
as unpleasant anymore that's like um
dealing with the secondary result of the
symptom basically of the illness rather
than the illness itself which is the
fact that when things are
unpleasant doesn't matter what whether
they're losery or not a losery or
whatever your mind is still liable to
Res resist them or when they're Pleasant
it's still liable to create for so yeah
you you keep assuming that the problem
is with the things in the world or with
other people where actually it isn't
yeah that's that's uh in general sense
so why how how then what is it that
would you you would have to do to free
yourself from suffering like how do you
if you don't have to prove that anything
is that if you don't have to prove to
yourself that things are not
real um clearly there is still some work to
um clearly there is still some work to
be done and there is still understanding
to be developed MH so so how could we
kind of
um paint a clear picture of what that
understanding is if it has nothing to do
with the things and denying their
existence or saying that there's some h
hidden kind of um
perceptual Distortion in on the level of the
Distortion in on the level of the
content of those
things what is it that you don't
understand in other words
yeah so when the things in the world are
allowed to be there whe it is other
people just whatever the things of the
world you're not denying that they're
there you're not rationalizing them away
by saying it's an illusion it's a dream
and and so on you just say they are
there you still notice that there're
suffering and now you are
asking um what is the right way for that
suffering to cease yeah so but
specifically in regard to understanding
because of course the whole idea is
based on the fact that there is
ignorance um so we're not denying that
there's ignorance we're not saying that
there nothing to be attained or
something like that MH there is a vast
lack of understanding there but it's not
on the level of like uh again pretty
much mystical information mhm that you
haven't gained and that if you were to
suddenly that's another wrong View that
you know if you if
you magically were to kind of get a
glimpse of this all your problems will
be immediately resolved whereas The Bu
does Clearly say there is no such thing
as sudden penetration to to knowledge
it's always gradual yeah so what is that
understanding that's missing well can I
just kind of butt in with another
thought before we try to answer that
question um I guess existentially
speaking even the notion that um
everything is false or like everything
is an illusion MH I think this is sort
of what a Pasco was saying but um that
is still blaming those things it's kind
of offloading the understanding because
I mean existentially
speaking um kind of the appearance of
things still belongs to those
things so if you're
understanding of understanding depends
on these things being otherwise then
that's not really in your control well
and and for that matter it's also
infinite CU how do you know that there
isn't the more Ultimate
Reality yeah so so it's you're just
chasing this kind of you're chasing this
thing that you yourself have creating in
other words um and uh so
words um and uh so
and I mean there's many angles you could
approach it but also the CST would say
that um you know whether it's past
present future um inferior or Superior coarse or
future um inferior or Superior coarse or
fine MH um regardless of what it is all
form all feeling all perception all
activities all Consciousness must be
seen in the same way in other words
there's nothing special so
if if your view is that by finding
something special you free yourself from
suffering well as much as you might want
to deny that you you might come up with
all these mystical views that oh look
this thing that I discovered is outside
of the five
Aggregates and and that's why it's quote
unquote the Escape MH but all you're
doing there is you're failing to apply
that blanket recognition that all form
because it doesn't matter how you SP
like anything mhm that is Arisen has to
be within those five Aggregates yeah
which includes the idea that there might
be something outside of the eist it
doesn't matter what perception it is
what what kind of yeah like the most um
exalted uh sense of of other worldly
yeah kind of sanctury from
everything well it's felt you can
already see that it's felt because
clearly you regard it as pleasant so it
it it's already within the five are
doesn't matter what you think so ideas
or ideals that you are striving after
that is also right it's mental but it's
fully within the
Aggregates even the most um acute
experience that you might get at the end
of your
meditation it doesn't matter it has to
be form feeling perception intention and
Consciousness you're completely confined
within those things so
that means that your meditation practice
ironically becomes quite real when you
adopt that view but also in a certain
sense a bit boring because now all your
Notions of what is esoteric and special
and mystical are going to be within
those Advocates yeah right so so it just
sort of flattens out so one needs to be
prepared that it might actually be
somewhat gray dull and boring but
ironically that's far more real exactly
yeah because
did you suffer what what was the thing
that you were suffering about like was
it what is the Ultimate Reality or was
it the mundane kind of Pleasure and Pain
when people were you know not doing well
as a as a so as what often say when um
you were separated from things that were
dear United with things that were not
dear sickness aging death bodily
displeasure mental displeasure those are
the things that you were suffering in
your guard too so why are you going in
this completely different direction yeah
that has nothing to do with it to to
escape the it's like I don't know I
have some kind of yeah physical ailment
ailment literally and I my Escape is
just to take like psychotic mushrooms to
to take myself to this completely
different dimension and then I I have
this magical expectation that I'll be
able to keep up that altered state
forever so that I never have to get
United with the old things again so now
going back to the pre previous
question if that's not understanding
then what is the understanding that you
develop such that you don't suffer
anymore why the same mundane things are
there because the five Aggregates are
the
mundane while stopping ignoring the fact
that well that those things are well
that whatever you perceive no matter how
special is still
within perception MH and no matter what
you feel no matter how pleasant it's still
feel no matter how pleasant it's still
within feeling MH so how how what would
be what are you trying to achieve by
cultivating that understanding I guess
well not resisting the things the way
they are exactly yeah so there is no
more magical piece of the puzzle that's
magical piece of the puzzle that's
missing anything more hidden than the
fact that when pain is there you resist
it when pleasure is there you cannot
help yourself but to want more of it and
that's the entire Samar from the
most kind of but now uh everyday things
to to the most
subtle kind of um feathers of
immaterial Realms and all this stuff the
entire thing is the same thing just
feeling not being understood and
actually the Buddhist said
um somebody who understands the three
feelings understands the origin
gratification and no the gratification
danger and Escape in regard to the three
feelings he says there is nothing more
that they need to do the work done and
there was no at no point they abandon
the quote unquote mundane reality which
is precisely those
feelings um so yeah in other words the
um so yeah in other words the
understanding that you have to cultivate
is is well that's actually what how he
would always phrase it like
gratification danger and Escape so you
understand um why was it that you were um
um why was it that you were um
passionate towards whatever you were
passionate towards and um you understand
why it's dangerous to be passionate
towards it and when you fully completely
understand that that passion is like as
sisters would say um putting your head
in a shopping
block um as we discussed in one of the
previous talks then you won't have to
wish for the passion not to be there it
will have to go
because the passion was based on you
still regarding those things as uh
sources of gratification like emphas
well emphasizing let's say the
gratification aspect and that's the
ignorance it's as simple as that it's
not being sufficiently clear about the
fact that what you regard as pleasant
it's real as such it's it's there there
is a pleasant aspect to it but it comes
with this kind of
um s simultaneous Danger
perel like uh I think this s also gave a
simil that it's like a like a razor
blade that is honey smeared all over it
and you can't help yourself but to keep
licking it and cutting yourself at the
same time and uh and that's all so you
time and uh and that's all so you
wouldn't need to because see actually
it's not just you wouldn't need to go
and chase after the Ultimate Reality you
realize the Ultimate Reality isn't
ultimate at all like you are kind of
defining it as such mhm because of your
assumption but it still is as I said
before it still is pleasant and there is
still a gratification there there is
still a danger there and there is still
an escape there but because you kind of
stopped at the content of how special it
is you didn't realize that actually it
had to be included within the same exact
principle so um so appearences are VI
yeah that's yeah and in that sense all
there is is is what appears yeah there's
appearance is reality to that extent
yeah and actually speaking about that
there's this that where um the Buddha
kind of alludes to this whole view that
things are quote unquote quote unquote
not real um it's
2294 it says because I do not argue with
the world it is the world that argues
with me one whose speech is aligned with
the dhma does not argue with anyone in
the world what the wise deem as not
existing I to say does not exist what
the wise deem as existing I to say
exists and what do the wise deem as not
existing which I to say does not exist
form that is permanent Everlasting
eternal and imperishable feeling
perception activities Consciousness that
is permanent Everlasting Eternal and
imperishable this is what the wise deem
is not existing which I to say does not
exist and what do the wise deem as
existing which I to say exists form that
is impermanent suffering and perishable
emphasis on it exists feeling perception
choices Consciousness that is
impermanent suffering imperishable this
is what the wise deem as existing which
I do say
exists there exists a mundane phenomenon
in the world and that is what the dooga
awakens to and comprehends having
awakened to and having having awakened
to it and comprehended it he teaches
asserts establishes clarifies analyzes
and reveals it and what is that mundane
phenomenon in the world form is a
mundane phenomenon in the world feeling
perception activities Consciousness is a
Mund phenomenon in the world that theal
awakens to and comprehends then he
explains teaches asserts establishes
clarifies analyze it analyzes and
reveals it this being so what can I do
about a foolish ordinary person blind
and sightless who does not know and
see suppose in other words somebody who
thinks that things don't exist even
though he's clearly saying that there
are things that exist yeah Suppose there
was a blue water lily or a pink or White
Lotus though it sprouted and grew in the
water it would rise up above the water
and stand with no water clinging to it
in the same way though the Tata has been
born and has grown up in the world he
lives having overcome the world
unsullied by the world
world
so that last
simile almost says it all
like how what what is it that makes you
be so given that the mundane things
exist it's not that they
don't um what is it that makes you get
sullied by them what is it that makes
the Lotus become soiled by the water but by
Lotus become soiled by the water but by
the muddy water yeah
mhm is it the things themselves
well like you were saying before passion
towards the desire and
must yeah
yeah
so it's that simple really not
understanding that things are not worthy
of passion you have passion towards them
that's the kind of beginningless state
as the said you cannot find a reason why
passion is there just wherever you look
it's it's going to you're going to find
that it's there already you didn't
created uh as a matter of choice it's
the fact that you
have IND indirectly kind of generated it
through your choices of rooted in
passion
so that's something that many people
would understand like you know passion
the Buddha talks about um giving up
passion aversion and delusion and he
says that nibana is the sensation of
passion diversion and
delusion now
yeah so just to pause here now for a
minute so if you become attached to
material things in the
world then you are giving power to
things that are inherently
powerless because you can't now be
without them right so that's the that's the
them right so that's the that's the
foolishness of of becoming attached to
things in the world then seeing that you
are stuck you want to deny the reality
of those things by saying that they are
illusory whereas actually it is due to
the wrong choices that you allowed
yourself to become attached to them
that's the issue and our amount of
denying the reality of those things is
going to undo the attachment that caused
the problem yeah so you make the house
dirty and then your solution is to
demolish the whole thing in cleaning it
up yeah because it's quicker of course
so
um but then given that people know that
again passion aversion and delusion
that's like basic Buddhist the dogma and
you know has to be abandoned and Nana is
the sensation of those three things
almost everybody knows that um so if
we're saying well that's what wisdom is
then somebody might say well I already
know that so but I'm not enlightened yet
so why is
that what what is there that's
missing the session of those
things yeah um but uh so basically how
let's say how would they bring about the
sensation of those things if it's not
through accessing some Ultimate Reality
if if you kind of cannot help but be
exposed to the Same Old Mundane boring
form feeling perception intention and
Consciousness then how can
you um as as the S says how can you kind
of Rise
Above um all of that without then having
to step into alternate
reality well by completely stopping to
engage with any of those things on any
level B verbal and mental yeah so I mean
it's it's I think we'll probably
repeated in every single talk but uh
it's uh the the reason why the the
uh the the reason why the the
same um knowledges that and and kind of
to some extent intellectual information
that you
have is not seen in such a way that it
would free you from suffering is because
yes you know in principle that form is
impermanent suffering not self but do
you live as if that's the case or do you
still act like someone who thinks that
certain forms are Pleasant uh are
permanent and are yours and it's as
simple as that so you cannot at the same
time um expect that that you will be
that that that that same information
that you have will be sinking in on the
level that it must for the passion to
dissipate if you continue to do the
things that are fully rooted in that
same passion so it's it's that simple
and then if you were to actually go
through like that's why when the Buddha
would talk about the final discernment
like to someone for the first time he
wouldn't start by by saying like um oh
yeah nothing exists um it's impermanent
and uh you know you just have to find
that hidden reality and all your
problems will be solved you would say no
first canman hears the the teaching
acquires Faith then they go forth they
they take on the precepts uh virtue
sensor trint gives on the whole
description of the grad training the
work of purifying the Mind from un
wholesome St States and then when the
mind is sufficiently purified they
understand what the Ultimate Reality no
they understand uh suffering the origin
of suffering the sensation of suffering
and the the way that leads to the
sensation of suffering they understand
um the defilements the origin of
defilements the cation of defilements
and the way that leads to the cation of
defilements and then once that that's
done it says um there's nothing more to
be done craving is u being is destroyed
and uh they abide at ease until the
Aggregates break apart
so um that's the part that's missing in
other words you have the information you
you know
that um you've read about the four no
truths you you have some recognition of
the three characteristics whichever
aspect of the teaching you you might
want to to focus on but um you're not
living in according to it in accordance
with it you still live and it says um
the inside of everything that is liable
to arise is liable to
cease now you um again might look for some
now you um again might look for some
magical experience where you going get
that Insight but um what you actually have to
Insight but um what you actually have to
look at to to see is am I living in such
a way that some things that are Li to
arise am I trying to to not make to make
them never
cease am I acting in such a way that I
assume or hope that I could maintain
some things or alternative you want to
get rid of that yeah exactly so because
another one is like the the whole ties
in with this whole um um view of of
Ultimate Reality and and hidden
perceptions is like the the flux like
the constant change mhm then when you
have something that makes you feel pain
you you conceive of the solution as
being to to tell yourself oh this will
pass this two shall pass this isn't
permanent it's all constantly changing
it's just molecules coming and going it
it does so either you deny the reality
of it by saying it's constantly changing
therefore it has no Essence and it's all
an illusion failing to see that you
actually still suffering so that's L
your contradiction well more more accurately
contradiction well more more accurately
like if you had actually understood that
it's liable to change then why are you
trying to get rid of it through that
same U you know supposedly right Insight
but you realize what is your attitude
what is your implied view there yeah
it's like no no actually I'm not sure
that it's going to pass away so that's
why I need to kind of to do something
about it so to that extent you are not
rightly patiently enduring whatever has
a vision yeah and that's why you try to
do it many of these things understand
the impermanence understand suffering
understand not self without having
develop virtue without having develop
sens strain without having developed the
gra training you will be acting out of
your sing Old Tendencies of of
impatience of craving of trying to get
rid of things and uh for that very
reason alone the the misconceiving of
things as permanent misconceiving of CRA
not seeing even your own craving
um all of that is still going to be
there so that's why that's the that's
the prerequisite even though it's not
the dhama there is no dama without
it yeah so by so due to Once impatience
for example which is rooted in the view
that it will not go away you will
actually you keep reinforcing The View
that those things are permanent and that
is why you should do something about it
and as long as that's what you do you're
you're not going to see that they are in
fact impermanent yeah so the way to
actually comp to see things as
impermanent which does not mean that
they are constantly changing is
ironically to endure those things which
are real and are there and during same
with not self if you like it's it's
quite amusing that sometimes the not
self idea would be re-explained as like
oh it's it's empty of inherent Essence
meaning like again another way of saying
it doesn't really exist and then you're
supposed to apply that view to
everything you counter especially when
it makes you suffer yeah and uh and why
is it that you're doing
that yeah because you're taking it
personally if you wouldn't be taking it
personally it wouldn't be making you
suffer in the first place yeah so you
realize this is the level where these
things have to be understood on the
level of as we often say the intention
behind your action why am I doing this m
that's where you will be holding all
these assumptions and Views um
so yes it's something active that you're
doing and all these methods are too late
you're already struck by suffering and
try to do something about it yeah and
and it will only last for a limited
amount of time whatever effect you get
out of these out of pasting these views
over your experience will will only last
a limited amount of time and that's why
you need to keep renewing it if you
haven't done the formal meditation where
you access the Ultimate Reality again
for a while you will quickly find that
you know you cannot actually over
overrun the fact
that Pleasure and Pain do arise I might
tell myself all I want that that is not
real and there this other dimension
that's more real than it but um the the
the kind of raw fact of of of it not
actually caring about you and what you
think about it will reveal itself again
um yeah and how do you know that the
Ultimate Reality is not more painful
yeah well ultimately it is because you
realize um the the simple fact of
needing to run away from things is
precisely the reason why you're
suffering yeah so it's it's actually and
and that's why the Buddha said there is
right Liberation and and there is wrong
Liberation so even though these things
might you might get a sense that they're
liberating you from the suffering um
through that same
Liberation uh you're inadvertently
cultivating the same thing that gave
rise to the problem to begin with so you
kind of it's like a way of um getting
rid of the symptoms a way that obscures
the symptoms while actually still making
the actual illness worse So then
whenever you stop um hiding those
symptoms you will probably find that the
illness has actually become worse and
that's why what often happens like when
you become when you find safety in these
these kind of higher perceptions or
whatever and and then you don't get to
do it for a while you will see that
things actually affect you twice as much
because you've been cultivating weakness
by by running away from it yeah because
why would you restrain yourself and
question your greed hatred and illusion
if you still assume that the solution is
finding this Ultimate Reality so it's a
wrong view but also it prevents you from
actually seeing what the view work is
and that will also exactly happen like
that's why then yeah the whole virtue
sensor strin gets becomes conditional
only for as long as I still haven't
achieved this High reality and once I do
all of this becomes secondary because it
was never real to begin with um
so well that's that's what makes it a
wrong View the fact that it doesn't lead
to freedom from suffering exactly it's
not it's not like it's a wrong view
because it's false and it also doesn't
happen to lead to free suffering that is
The Benchmark for yeah well it it it
doesn't lead to removing the causes of
suffering it might remove that's why I
said like the symptom and the illness so
the the the symptoms of of you actually
experiencing Pleasant feelings at that
time uh you can suppress that like but
mind you you don't need the Buddha for
that you can do do that in million
different ways so um but the cause which
is a craving the same thing that you're
still cultivating toward the toward
these higher realities that's still
there it's just that kind of the it will
have a delayed effect so it'll catch up
on you later on it won't it won't be
apparent right then and there that um
that same attitude that you're
cultivating toward these things is is
what uh generated the the same suffering
that you were running away from in the
past is the same with sensity actually
in the moment it feels like it's great
only afterwards when you're kind of cut
away from uh that which you were welcoming
from uh that which you were welcoming
you realize the the suffering that
you've the liability to suffering that
you've been uh
feeding so you create that dependence on
something that's higher and now that
higher thing becomes your addiction
becomes that which you need to maintain
and that's why the Buddha said the one
who gives things up rightly he does so
without taking up something
new yeah because somebody might have an
idea of some high or ultimate reality
and in order to go there they might in
fact abandon a whole bunch of let's say
other attachments or lower things but
still for the wrong reason for the for
the wrong reason so they can replacing
one craving with a more s yeah so but
what we are now saying is that all of
that giving up still needs to happen but
in the absence of uh you going somewhere
else basically yeah and and that's
what's going to make it as you said it's
going to make it more boring because you
realize yeah I'm not going to get some
magical reward out of this it's just I
will have the same things but uh I won't
suffer anymore in regards to yeah and
that doesn't sound as exhilarating yeah
but uh well that's that's how life is
it's it's it's um the things that are
shiny and pleasant and quick fixes are
usually just gimmicks
yeah or it's much more challenging as
well I could listen to this and think I
need to tighten up my restraint then I
need to start giving things up I need to
see the I need to see the danger not
just this
gratification so um I need to see
um I need to see a rope as a snake
instead of a snake of a rope and so I
just replace the Beautiful with like the
ugly and I just deny that
aspect yeah I could
um yeah thinking I'm practicing
mindfulness yeah actually that's another
thing I wanted to go back to so the
right type of wisdom since that's that's
what we started to talk
with is not that the snake the Rope is
not a
snake it's that even when it is a snake
and it's actually a poisonous Viper and
it's actually biting you right in the
neck you don't
suffer that's what the wisdom is it's
not that oh this is not what it
is yeah well that would be the goal of
the the practice let's say so that's
what your understanding is measured by
it's not how much you can pretend that
things are not what what they are or
make them appear otherwise it's how when
the worst case scenario comes and you
cannot escape from it you cannot go left
right up or down front or back then the
question is has the work been done or
not yeah yeah
and there was one more s that I wanted
to
read to
um following the same threat so that it
says that the the eight um worldly
phenomena loc so
that's another common teaching that suas
it says because the eight worldly
phenomena follow the world around and
the world follows the eight worldly
phenomena around what eight gain and
loss of ultimate
realities uh honor and dishonor blame
and praise pleasure and displeasure
these eight worldly phenomena follow the
world around and the world follows the
eight worldly phenomena
around for an unlearned ordinary person
gain and loss honor and dishonor blame
and blame and praise and pleasure and
displeasure arise and so do they for a
learned and Noble
disciple what then is the difference
between a learned Noble disciple and an
ordinary unlearned person so that's what
we were saying before like if if it's
just about these same mundane things
what is it that you don't understand and
so it
says um because gain arises for an
unlearned ordinary person they don't
reflect this gain has arisen for me it's
impermanent suffering imp perishable
they don't understand it as it is F
arises honor dishonor blame praise
displeasure uh pleasure
displeasure uh
arise uh they don't reflect this
displeasure has arisen for me it's
impermanent suffering imperishable they
don't understand it as it is so gain and
loss honor and dishonor blame and and
praise and pleasure and
displeasure endure with a grip on their
mind they Embrace gain and resist loss
they Embrace Fame and resist resist
disgrace they Embrace praise and oppose
blame they Embrace pleasure and oppose
displeasure uh being thus engaged in
embracing embracing and resisting
they're not freed from birth aging and
death from sorrow lamentation
displeasure sadness and distress they're
not freed from suffering I say now
because gain arises for a learn Noble
disciple they do reflect this gain has
arisen for me it's impermanent suffering
imperishable they understand it as it is
loss honor dishonor blame praise
pleasure displeasure uh they reflect this is
displeasure uh they reflect this is
pleasure has arisen for me it's
impermanent suffering and perishable
they understand it as it is so when gain
uh and loss honor and dishonor blame and
praise and pleasure and
displeasure arise they don't endure with
a grip on their mind they don't Embrace
gain or resist loss they don't Embrace
honor or resist dishonor they don't
Embrace praise or resist blame they
don't Embrace pleasure pleasure or
resist displeasure having given up uh
embracing and resisting they're free
from birth aging and death from sorrow
lamentation displeasure sadness and
distress they're freed from suffering I
say and then it ends with um this is the
difference between a learned Noble
disciple and an unlearned ordinary
person and then it finishes with the
verse gain and loss honor and dishonor blame
gain and loss honor and dishonor blame
and pl blame and praise and pleasure and
displeasure these qualities among people
are impermanent transient and
perishable uh an intelligent and mindful
person having known these things sees
that they're perishable pleasing
phenomena don't disturb their mind nor
do they Harbor resistance against the
undesirable both Embrace embracing and
resisting are dispelled and ended they
are no more knowing the stainless
sorrowless State they gone beyond beyond
being understand
rightly so the stainless s the state
being sensation of passion sensation of
complete cooling down the B of Um
passion and diversion and ignorance in
regard to the eight worldly things that
you cannot escape from even if you want
to yeah so a noble disciple understands
that right gain has come to me but it's
impermanence yeah so that gain is real
but it's impermanence exactly yeah that
same he does not he does not say that
gain is impermanent therefore it's not
real no that gain is real and it is
impermanent and that's precisely what he
has understood so rather than denying
the gain what disase is the danger in
now becoming infatuated with that gain
because it's
impermanence see it's it's much
more in a sense mundane but as you said
before the reason why it's not as
attractive is because it reveals this
whole additional dimension of work that
you have to do yeah not things that will
just sort themselves out by just seeing
them so Ultimate Reality is with those
Malaysia and your your responsibility
yeah yeah the responsibility that yeah
it's it's shame not
because I'm just not fortunate that I
haven't discovered this yet even though
I've been practicing for 20 years it's
if if you're still suffering it's
because on some level you must still be
fueling the fire Bion there's no other
explanation for it for